Hi, welcome back!
Previously, we
discussed frameworks
and controls in general.
In this video,
you'll learn about
specific frameworks and
controls that organizations
can voluntarily use to minimize
risks to their data
and to protect users.
Let's get started!
The CIA triad is a foundational model
that helps inform how
organizations consider
risk when setting up systems
and security policies.
CIA stands for confidentiality,
integrity, and availability.
Confidentiality means that
only authorized users
can access specific
assets or data.
For example, strict
access controls that
define who should and should
not have access to data,
must be put in place to ensure
confidential data remains safe.
Integrity means the data is
correct, authentic,
and reliable.
To maintain integrity,
security professionals
can use a form of
data protection like encryption
to safeguard data from
being tampered with.
Availability means data is
accessible to those who are
authorized to access it.
As an example, a
director may have
more access to certain data
than a department manager
because directors usually
oversee more employees.
Let's define a term
that came up during
our discussion of the CIA triad:
asset.
An asset is an item perceived as having
value to an organization.
And value is determined by the cost
associated with the
asset in question.
For example, an application
that stores sensitive data,
such as social security
numbers or bank accounts,
is a valuable asset
to an organization.
It carries more risk
and therefore requires
tighter security
controls in comparison
to a website that shares
publicly available news content.
As you may remember,
earlier in the course,
we discussed frameworks
and controls in general.
Now, we'll discuss a specific
framework developed by
the U.S.-based National
Institute of Standards
and Technology:
the Cybersecurity
Framework, also
referred to as the NIST CSF.
The NIST Cybersecurity
Framework is
a voluntary framework that
consists of standards,
guidelines, and best practices
to manage cybersecurity risk.
It's important to become
familiar with this framework
because security teams use it as
a baseline to manage
short and long-term risk.
Managing and mitigating
risks and protecting
an organization's assets from
threat actors are key goals
for security professionals.
Understanding the
different motives
a threat actor may have,
alongside identifying
your organization's
most valuable assets
is important.
Some of the most
dangerous threat actors
to consider are
disgruntled employees.
They are the most dangerous
because they often have
access to sensitive information
and know where to find it.
In order to reduce
this type of risk,
security professionals would use
the principle of availability,
as well as organizational
guidelines
based on frameworks to ensure
staff members can only access
the data they need to
perform their jobs.
Threat actors originate
from all across the globe,
and a diverse workforce
of security professionals
helps organizations identify
attackers' intentions.
A variety of perspectives
can assist organizations in
understanding and mitigating
the impact of
malicious activity.
That concludes our
introduction to
the CIA triad and
NIST CSF framework,
which are used to
develop processes to
secure organizations and
the people they serve.
You may be asked in
an interview if you
know about security
frameworks and principles.
Or you may be asked to
explain how they're
used to secure
organizational assets.
In either case,
throughout this program,
you'll have multiple
opportunities
to learn more about them
and apply what we've discussed
to real-world situations.
Coming up, we'll discuss
the ethics of security.
See you soon!