The security industry
is constantly evolving,
but many present-day attacks
are not entirely new.
Attackers often alter or
enhance previous methods.
Understanding past attacks can
provide direction
for how to handle
or investigate incidents in
your job as a security analyst.
First, let's go over
a couple of key terms
that will support
your understanding
of the attacks we'll discuss.
A computer virus is
malicious code written
to interfere with
computer operations and cause
damage to data and software.
The virus attaches itself to
programs or documents
on a computer,
then spreads and infects
one or more computers
in a network.
A worm is a type of
computer virus that can
duplicate and spread on its
own without human involvement.
Today, viruses are more commonly
referred to as malware,
which is software designed
to harm devices or networks.
Two examples of early
malware attacks that we'll
cover are the Brain virus
and the Morris worm.
They were created by
malware developers to
accomplish specific tasks.
However, the developers
underestimated the impact
their malware would
have and the amount
of infected computers
there would be.
Let's take a closer look
at these attacks and
discuss how they helped shape
security as we know it today.
In 1986, the Alvi brothers
created the Brain virus,
although the intention of
the virus was to track
illegal copies of
medical software
and prevent pirated licenses,
what the virus actually
did was unexpected.
Once a person used a pirated
copy of the software,
the virus-infected
that computer.
Then, any disk that was
inserted into the computer
was also infected.
The virus spread
to a new computer
every time someone used
one of the infected disks.
Undetected, the virus
spread globally within
a couple of months.
Although the
intention was not to
destroy data or hardware,
the virus slowed down
productivity and
significantly impacted
business operations.
The Brain virus fundamentally
altered the computing industry,
emphasizing the
need for a plan to
maintain security
and productivity.
As a security analyst,
you will follow and maintain
strategies put in
place to ensure
your organization has a plan
to keep their data
and people safe.
Another influential computer
attack was the Morris worm.
In 1988, Robert Morris developed
a program to assess the
size of the internet.
The program crawled the web
and installed itself onto
other computers to
tally the number
of computers that were
connected to the internet.
Sounds simple, right?
The program, however, failed to
keep track of the
computers and had
already compromised and
continued to re-install
itself until the computers ran
out of memory and crashed.
About 6,000 computers
were affected,
representing 10% of the
internet at the time.
This attack cost millions of
dollars in damages due to
business disruptions
and the efforts
required to remove the worm.
After the Morris worm,
Computer Emergency
Response Teams,
known as CERTs®, were
established to respond to
computer security incidents.
CERTs still exist today,
but their place in the
security industry has
expanded to include
more responsibilities.
Later in this program,
you'll learn more about
the core functions of
these security teams
and gain hands-on practice
with detection and
response tools.
Early attacks played a key role
in shaping the current
security industry.
And coming up, we'll discuss how
attacks evolved in
the digital age.